Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is צדי בית, tzadi-beiz,
but we are a little bit behind. We're in צדי אלף עמוד
בית tzadi-alef amud-beis and we're in the middle of a whole discussion
about whether the כולן kulan in the משנה mishna where it says
that if the woman gets married שלא ברשות, shelo birshus, which in
the simple sense of the משנה mishna means without any permission from
בית דין, beis din, just unilaterally on her own. But according to
the גמרא gemara actually means with a stronger basis with two witnesses
but didn't need the special powers of בית דין. beis din. Anyway,
it says under those circumstances she can go back to her husband.
And the question is: is that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon's statement, who
generally is lenient and says that the kid isn't a ממזר mamzer
from the first husband, that possibly she'll never need a גט get
from the second guy, or is that a תנא קמא דברי הכל?
Tanna Kamma divrei hakol? And there's obviously a very relevant question of
how we פסקן pasken that רב, Rav, who presumably understood it to
be רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon's statement, nevertheless said that's how we rule.
But if you're going to make it רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon's statement,
it will raise serious questions about how we rule or not. So
that's the question: is it דברי הכל? divrei hakol? And the argument
that it's a דברי הכל divrei hakol is because if the woman
based herself on, again the way the גמרא gemara's understanding שלא ברשות,
shelo birshus, on two witnesses, then she's an אנוסה. anusa. She totally
had absolute no fault and it was totally out of her control.
She did everything right. There's nothing she could have done better. And
therefore, how can we give her all of these negative consequences? That's
the argument that everybody should agree in this case she does not
have those consequences. Let's take a look now as the גמרא gemara
continues and it's going to question exactly that point. Is it necessarily
true that these consequences are only when there's an element of fault
involved? So let's take a look. תא שמע, ta shma, come here.
מתיב עולא. meisiv Ulla. עולא Ulla asked about six lines from the
top on צדי אלף עמוד בית. tzadi-alef amud-beis. עולא Ulla asked: מי
אמרינן מה הוה לה למעבד? mi amrinan mai hava la lema'avad?
Do we say, oh, there was nothing else she could have done
and therefore
we won't she wouldn't be you know she couldn't so it would
not be right to have her suffer these consequences? Do we really
make that argument? והתנן, vehatnan, we have a משנה, mishna, there's a
string of משניות mishnayos in גיטין Gittin where it says different types
of scenarios and the consequence of all of those scenarios is exactly
the consequence of our משנה: mishna: תצא מזה ומזה והולד
ממזר מזה ומזה, teitzei mizeh umizeh ve'havalad mamzer mizeh umizeh, you know
and she loses her כתובה kesubah and her מזונות mezonos and all
the consequences in the משנה. mishna. There's a series of scenarios in
משניות mishnayos in גיטין Gittin that the same thing is true. If
she marries a second guy and somehow it was all turned out
to be wrong and she has to suffer all of these negative
consequences. So let's take a look at those cases and see if
those cases she was at fault in those cases or not. והתנן,
vehatnan, we taught in the משנה: mishna: כתב לשם מלכות שאינה הוגנת.
kasav leshem malchus she'eina hogenes. The גט get was written and when
it was dated it was dated by a kingship, a kingdom, like
X years for so-and-so king that was somehow not seen as a
fit kingdom, you know some type of a kingdom that was not
recognized in that in that locale. או לשם מלכות מדי או לשם
מלכות יון, o leshem malchus Madai o leshem malchus Yavan, for the
kingdom of for the Medes or for the Greeks. לבנין הבית לחורבן
הבית, levinyan habayis lechurban habayis, or for the years counting from the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or from the destruction of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. All those, you know, what's the big deal? But somehow
that did not conform to the standard way of dating. היה במזרח
וכתב במערב, haya bemizrach vechasav bama'arav, or he was in the east
and it was written in the west. תוספות Tosafos points out although
it sounds like it was that the סופר, sofer, the scribe was
in the east. The real issue is not where the סופר sofer
was. The real issue is where the עדים eidim were when they
signed it. So anyway, but it was taking place in the east
and the location of it was was written incorrectly in the גט.
get. במערב וכתב במזרח, bama'arav vechasav bemizrach, or the west and it
was written the east. So anyway there were some technical problems with
the dating or with the location of the גט. get. Nothing you
would say would be that huge. Nevertheless, the משנה mishna says תצא
מזה ומזה וכל הדרכים האלו בה. teitzei mizeh umizeh vechol hadrachim ha'eilu
bah. She has to get divorced from the first husband, the second
husband, if she went and remarried on the basis of this גט,
get, the kid from either one would be a ממזר, mamzer, all
of these negative consequences. So here, this poor woman! What is she
supposed to know about הלכות גיטין? hilchos Gittin? Her husband gave her
a גט get and now you're punishing her. So it sounds like
these consequences are not necessarily because she was at fault. It sounds
like it's something else. And again what I should say is that
this really argues for the other approach to the משנה, mishna, you
know the approach that Shamma Friedman sort of said that I suggested
before, which is not that all these consequences are to ensure that
she's going to do a good job investigating and there's some type
of a punishment and a קנס. knas. No! If there's some reason
to see it as if she is genuinely married to two men,
meaning halachically obviously she can't, but because we basically you know there's
enough of a perception that that's the reality, either because there was
you know witnesses and we told her she could remarry so we
gave her the allowance to remarry the second guy in our משנה,
mishna, or because you know it looked like a good גט get
and it really wasn't a pretty good גט get except for some
technicality, all those things then you have to deal what's the consequence
of being seen as being you know of as if you're married
to two men. And then all of these consequences result from the
reality of being married to two men. But it's not a punishment.
It's just a reality from this you know the consequences from this
reality. So that's what essentially the גמרא gemara is saying is, don't
say that it makes a difference one witness, two witness or whatever.
Yes, she's at fault. No. Look at the cases where she has
all these consequences where she's absolutely not at fault at all. One
minute. So that's the גמרא's Gemara proof. So let's see what the
גמרא's Gemara answer is. ואמאי ואי לימא מאי הוה לה למיעבד?
V'amai vai leima mai
hava leh leme'vad? What could she have done?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, איבעי לה לקרוא לגיטא. iba'ei leh
likro legita.
No, no, we'll say she was at fault, she should have read
the גט get and said, oh wait a minute, the place is
wrong, the dating is too, it's a funny dating. Of course, it's
funny, it's not like the date is wrong, it was just like
a non-conventional dating. What, we assume she knows? Anyway, but that's the
גמרא's Gemara answer. So let's take a look at the next משנה.
Mishnah. אמר רב שימי מבירא, Amar Rav Shimi mibeira, these are all
משניות, Mishnayot, you know, one next after next in גיטין, Gittin, not
necessarily in this order, but anyway. אמר רב שימי בר אשי, Amar
Rav Shimi bar Ashi, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear another
משנה: Mishnah: הקונס את יבמתו, Hakones et yevamto,
somebody, you know, marries his sister-in-law, does the act of יבום. yibum.
This is again a משנה Mishnah in גיטין. Gittin. והלכה צרתה, Vehalkha
tzaratah, then the co-wife goes ונישאת veniset and she marries another guy.
That seems completely legitimate. וניסת זו ונמצאת אילונית, Veniset zu venimtzeit ailonit,
but the woman it turns out that he did יבום yibum with
was an אילונית ailonit and therefore it wasn't a mean a good
act of יבום, yibum, right, because there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibum with an אילונית. ailonit. And therefore the צרה tzarah really still
needs חליצה chalitzah or יבום. yibum. So what did the צרה tzarah
do? She went and she had married another guy, and retroactively it
turned out that she married the other guy while she still really
would have required an act of חליצה. chalitzah. So by the way,
it isn't even an act of adultery, it's just marrying another guy
without an act of חליצה. chalitzah. And her co-wife here had done
יבום. yibum. Nevertheless, what do we say when this is all discovered?
תצא מזה ומזה וכל הדרכים האלו בה. Teitzei mizeh umizeh vechol hadrachim
ha'elu bah. This צרה tzarah has to leave the first husband, the
guy she married. She can't have יבום yibum with the brother-in-law, and
all these negative consequences. So, my God, what did the צרה tzarah
co-wife do wrong? I mean an act of יבום yibum was done.
So the גמרא Gemara says ואמאי ואי לימא מאי הוה לה למיעבד?
V'amai vai leima mai havah leh leme'vad? What should she have done?
Says no, איבעי לה לאמתוני. iba'ei leh lamtonei. She should have waited
until it was, you know, given a time to see whether it
would turn out that the co-wife was an אילונית ailonit or not.
Seems crazy. How long is she supposed to wait? Fifteen years? I
mean, you know, I mean she's been married with this other co-wife
for the last ten years maybe. I mean, what does it mean?
Like so all of a sudden we've been learning all of מסכת
יבמות Masechet Yevamot and we say when one woman gets יבום, yibum,
you know, the צרה tzarah can go and remarry, and now we're
saying oh, but really you better wait a good ten, fifteen, twenty
years before you do it, because if it turns out that the
wife that the woman who had יבום yibum was an אילונית, ailonit,
you'll be, you know, you'll be really in big trouble. Right? Completely
bizarre. A, just the הלכה halakhah is is a shocker, you know,
number one, that that these are the consequences. We had no idea
these would be the consequences. And B, the גמרא's Gemara assumption that,
yes, she is at fault, she should have waited. Let's take a
look at the next case.
אמר אביי תא שמע, Amar Abaye ta shema, let's look at another
משנה Mishnah in גיטין. Gittin. כל העריות שאמרו פוטרות צרותיהן. Kol ha'arayot
she'amru potrot tzaroteihen.
All the עריות, arayot, right, you know, a guy who has his
brother dies and one of the wives is a, I don't know,
his, you know, his daughter or something like that, so it exempts
the co-wife. הלכו צרות ונישאו. Halchu tzarot venisu.
So again, the צרות tzarot went and they remarried. Okay, because, you
know, they're they're off the hook because one of the co-wives was
an ערוה. ervah. ונמצאו אלו אילוניות. Venimtzu elu ailoniyot.
But then it turned out that the co-wife who was an ערוה
ervah was an אילונית. ailonit. And if the co-wife who was an
ערוה ervah was an אילונית, ailonit, so it's not like she was
a מקח טעות, mekach taut, she's not really a co-wife. And therefore
the fact that she's an ערוה ervah doesn't exempt this woman from
having to have יבום yibum or חליצה. chalitzah. Right? You get the
case? Right? A guy died, one of the women was a the
other brother's daughter, let's say. So we said, oh okay, which one
of them is an ערוה, ervah, they're all exempt. But then it
turns out ten years later that the daughter was an אילונית. ailonit.
So it turns out retroactively that the other women weren't exempt. And
this poor woman, she went and she remarried, and now it turns
out that she needed חליצה. chalitzah. So what's the הלכה? halakhah? תצא
מזה ומזה וכל הדרכים האלו בה. Teitzei mizeh umizeh vechol hadrachim ha'elu
bah. All of the negative consequences. ואמאי? V'amai? Why? נימא מאי הוה
לה למיעבד? neima mai havah leh leme'vad? What could she have done?
No. Same answer. איבעי לה לאמתוני. Iba'ei leh lamtonei. She should have
waited to see whether this daughter who was a co-wife, this ערוה,
ervah, whether she was going to be an אילונית ailonit or not.
So again, of course it's a real shocker. All the cases that
we've been learning so far, that women, you know, once you do
יבום yibum or if a woman's an ערוה, ervah, the other women
are free to remarry. Now we're finding out that if it turns
out we made a mistake then retroactively they're going to suffer all
of these tremendous negative consequences. What's more than that is that the
גמרא Gemara is saying that to some degree it's their fault, they
should have waited, which is seems like a very, you know, very
harsh. So let's take a look. אמר רבא תא שמע. Amar Rava
ta shema. Let's look at another case. כתב סופר גט לאיש ושוברו
לאשה. Katav sofer get le'ish veshovro le'ishah.
The סופר sofer wrote a גט get for the man that that
he's going to give it to his wife, and he wrote a
receipt for the woman. Not a receipt for the גט, get, but
that once the כתובה ketubah would be paid off, the woman would
hand the husband a receipt for payment of the כתובה. ketubah. Okay?
וטעה. Veta'ah.
And then when it was time to deliver the documents, the סופר
sofer made a mistake. ונתן גט לאשה ושובר לאיש. Venatan get le'ishah
veshover le'ish. He gave the גט get to the woman and the
שובר shover to the man. And they assumed that they had the
right documents, but they actually had the wrong ones. ונתנו זה לזה
וזה לזה. Venatnu zeh lazeh vezeh lazeh. And they gave each other
their documents. So the man gave the woman the שובר shover thinking
it was a גט, get, and the woman after the כתובה ketubah
was paid gave the man a גט get thinking it was the
שובר. shover. Okay? So basically there was no גט get given at
all.
So what's הלכה? halacha?
ולאחר זמן הרי גט יוצא מתחת ידי האיש ul'achar zman harei get
yotze mitachat yedei ha-ish and then a while later the man is
saying, Oh yeah, my wife paid up her כתובה, kesuvah, look, here's
the receipt, and he hands it to somebody and somebody says this
isn't the receipt, it's a גט. get. ושובר מתחת ידי האשה v'shovre
mitachat yedei ha-ishah and the woman says, Yeah, I got a גט
get from my husband, look at this, and he says this isn't
a גט, get, this is a receipt. Okay, so what do you
say? So תצא מזה ומזה וכל הדרכים האלו בה, teitzei mizeh u'mizeh
v'chol hadrachim ha-eilu bah, she has to get divorced from the second
husband and from the first and all the negative consequences. ואמאי נימא
מה הוה לה למעבד, v'amai neima mah havah lah l'meivad, what should
she have done? Like he just did what the סופר sofer gave
up the documents, what should she have done? No, איבעי לה למקרי
לגיטה, ibayei lah l'mikrei l'gittah, she should have read the גט get
that was given to her and realize this isn't a גט, get,
it's a receipt. Now of course you realize that the irony about
all of this is that the vast number of people were illiterate.
So the idea a) that she should have read it and b)
also some of these things that she should have realized that there
was a technical problem, I mean here maybe it would have been
obvious if she was literate, but some of them it was a
technical problem and to say she should have realized that and it
was her fault is very strange. Let's look at the last one.
תא שמע ta shema come and hear, אמר רב אשי תא שמע
amar Rav Ashi ta shema come and hear, שינה שמו ושמה ושם
עירו ושם עירה. shina shemo u'shemah v'shem iro v'shem iroh. If the
גט get had a wrong name of the husband or her wrong
name or the wrong name of the city or her wrong name
of her city, תצא מזה ומזה וכל הדרכים האלו בה, teitzei mizeh
u'mizeh v'chol hadrachim ha-eilu bah, and then it turns out that that's
the גט get she's using and she had remarried, she has to
get divorced from both and all the consequences etc. So the גמרא
gemara says ואמאי נימא מה הוה לה למעבד, v'amai neima mah havah
lah l'meivad, same question. What should she have done? How should she
have realized that there was a problem? No, איבעי לה למקרי לגיטה,
ibayei lah l'mikrei l'gittah, she should have read the גט get and
say, Hey, this is weird, this isn't exactly my name, they spelled
it wrong, or they got a different variation, whatever,
and she should have asked somebody. So therefore, yes, she is at
fault. אמר רבינא תא שמע. amar Ravina ta shema. Come and hear,
says רבינא, Ravina, come and hear, כנסה בגט קרח. kanasah b'get kireiach.
A man married a woman after she had received a bald גט.
get. What is a bald גט? get? So there's something called a
גט מקושר, get mekushar, a
sewed-up גט, get, that basically the way it works is, here, can
I use a piece of paper here? Okay, so the way it
works is you basically, you write the גט, get,
okay, and then what you do is you fold it, okay? Here,
you have the גט get on the inside, you fold it, and
then one witness signs his name on the fold, right? You know,
you sometimes do that when you're like writing a recommendation for somebody,
you sign when there used to be things called letters. Anyway, and
then you fold it again, and then whatever, and then you write
your name, the next witness writes his name on the next fold,
right? And then you fold it again and then the next witness
writes his name and there'd be many more than two witnesses. So,
well, whatever, we'll see more about that when we get to גיטין.
gittin. One of the points is to make כהנים kohanim spend more
time before they divorce their wives because it's going to be such
an elaborate process, so cool off a little bit. Anyway, so a
גט קרח get kireiach is that on one of the folds there
was no signature. So it's bald, it's got a bald spot. Okay,
so a woman got a גט get that had that bald spot
on it and she got remarried,
תצא מזה ומזה teitzei mizeh u'mizeh etc., all the consequences once we
realize the problem. So what should she have done? So the גמרא
gemara says, no, איבעי לה למקרי לגיטה, ibayei lah l'mikrei l'gittah, she
should have read the גט. get. Of course, the point is she
did read the גט, get, everything was okay. She is supposed to
know this technical הלכה halacha that if one of the folds don't
have a signature? You know, so again, it's a little bit bizarre.
We have a very weighty evidence that all of these consequences are
in cases even when she's not at fault at all. And the
גמרא gemara therefore says, so you see, it's not about a fine
for her being at fault. For some reason some scenarios have all
these negative consequences and this really points to the idea, like I
said, which is the point that Shammai Friedman, sort of the way
he says in terms of reading this משנה, mishnah, that it has
nothing to do with the fact, or we can read it in
terms of the פשט, pshat, that it's not like we give all
these negative consequences to be an incentive for her to make sure
that she does a good job investigating. Because by the way, none
of that is relevant to all these cases, right? All these cases,
I guess if you wanted to you could say, well, we're going
to have all these negative consequences to make sure that the woman
makes sure there are no technical problems in the גט. get. But
come on, it's the woman's responsibility to make sure there are no
technical problems in the גט? get? So a) it's not only is
she not at fault, but it doesn't seem like it's there to
serve as a way of backing up the legitimacy of relying on
an עד אחד, eid echad, which is how the גמרא gemara explained
it. It seems like these negative consequences are just negative consequences. If
you go ahead and remarry another person and it turns out you're
still married to your first husband in certain cases where it really
looks like it was a legitimate second marriage, then and then it
turns out you're still married to the first husband, then you have
a reality of being as if it were married to two people.
These are natural negative consequences. That's really what it seems. So it
seems like it's not at all based on her being at fault,
it seems like it's not based on a need to use these
things to back up the testimony of עד אחד. eid echad. It's
just seen as a negative, as the natural negative consequences of some
certain cases. So the גמרא gemara says, if that's true, then unfortunately
there's a negative consequence of that. There's the outcome of that is
that then these will apply even in cases when there was absolutely
no fault of her. And therefore these should apply even when she
remarries based on two witnesses and therefore that statement that... that if
she does it שלא ברשות, shelo birshut, she's okay, it's, you don't
have these consequences, would not be דברי הכל, divrei hakol, because it
might not really matter if she was at fault or not at
fault, these consequences would always apply. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
tries to argue. Makes a very strong argument in that direction, but
it tries to answer. No, no, no, all these cases there was
an element of fault on her. But if she had no fault
like it was based on two witnesses, then you would not have
these consequences. Wait, let's see how the גמרא Gemara concludes. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. רב פפא סבר למעבד עובדא במה הויא
ולא
עבדה. Rav Pappa savar lemavad uvda bema havya velo avda. So רב
פפא Rav Pappa wanted to rule on a case based on this
principle of what could she have done? Meaning that she remarried based
on two witnesses, she had absolutely no fault, husband turned up alive,
and רב פפא Rav Pappa wanted to say she could go back
to her first husband. If she was not at fault, that statement
that she can go back to her first husband is not just
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's דברי הכל, divrei hakol, she was not
at fault, she can go back to her first husband. Okay, that
line in the משנה. Mishnah. אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
לרב פפא. Amar lei Rav Huna brei deRav Yehoshua leRav Pappa. So
רב הונא Rav Huna the son of רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua says
to רב פפא: Rav Pappa: והתניא כל הני מתנייתא? Vehatanya kol hanei
matnyata? What are all these משניות Mishnayot in גיטין Gittin
that make it clear that you have these consequences even when she's
not at fault? Who cares if she's at fault or not, you
still have these consequences. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to
him, ולאו שנינו? Velav shaninu? But we answered them. We gave reasons
with which she was at fault. But I still want to hold
that when she's literally not at fault at all, there's no fault
like two witnesses, then she can go back to her first husband.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him, ושינוייא ליקו
ולסמוך? Veshinuyei leiku velismoch?
What, we're going to rely on those answers? Meaning just because you
gave some answer, the פשט pshat of all those משניות Mishnayot is
not that way. The simple sense of all of the evidence is
that even when there's no fault, all these consequences apply. And therefore
that would be true even, it does, but not always, sometimes the
גמרא Gemara says אשינוייא דחיקא ליקו ולסמוך? ashinuyei dicheika leiku velismoch?
Okay,
so sometimes we do rely on weak answers. But he's saying give
me a break, you have all these משניות, Mishnayot, it's a very,
very weak answer. We should assume that even if she's not at
fault, these consequences apply and the line in the משנה Mishnah that
said when it's שלא ברשות shelo birshut she can go back, that's
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. But we don't פסקן pasken that way. That's
not assumed, and even when she's not at fault. So the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, so now let's just get to the two dots.
אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. So here's the line that's really
not, that really is the end of that סוגיא, sugya, but a
little of an additional line, additional point before we sort of take
a pause here. ולקלא לא חיישינן. Ulekala lo chaishinan. Now and we
are not, ולקלא לא חיישינן, ulekala lo chaishinan, and we're not concerned
about just, even though we're concerned if the husband shows up, or
we're concerned if there are witnesses that the husband is alive, and
we have all these negative consequences, if there's just rumors, we're not
concerned. So the גמרא Gemara says: האי קלא? Hai kala? What type
of a rumor?
אילימא קלא Ileima kala mean sound, there's talk about it.
אילימא קלא דבתר נישואין Ileima kala debatar nisuin the rumor emerges after
she remarried the second guy? האמר לה רב אשי חדא זימנא. Ha'amar
lah Rav Ashi chada zimna. רב אשי Rav Ashi already told us
this. דאמר רב אשי, De'amar Rav Ashi, כל קלא דבתר נישואין. kol
kala debatar nisuin. Any type of a rumor after marriage, not only
about the husband still being alive, let's say a woman marries a
כהן, Kohen, and then afterward that there's a rumor that maybe she
was a גרושה. grusha. Okay, any rumor that emerges after marriage, לא
חיישינן. lo chaishinan. We don't worry about it. She's already married. If
you want to make a problem in an existing marriage, you need
concrete evidence. If there's just some rumor, we're not going to worry
about it. Rumor before marriage is maybe different, but once she's already
married, unless you have concrete evidence, we're not going to do anything
about it. מהו דתימא, Mahu deteima, so he said it already. No,
I might have thought הואיל ואתאי לבי דינא ושרינן. ho'il ve'atai levei
dina vesharinan.
Since her husband, she was already married to her first husband, that
was sort of the status quo. And then she had to come
to בית דין, Beit Din, and בית דין Beit Din now had
to פסקן, pasken, maybe even based on one witness, on weak testimony,
to allow her to remarry, but already there was something substantial that
existed before she got married to the second guy, namely that she
had been married to the first guy. And there was a, and
we needed the power of בית דין Beit Din to allow her
to remarry, so maybe that already lays
a foundation כקלא דקמי נישואין דמי kekala dekamei nisuin dami that when
a rumor now comes out that her husband is still alive, it
would be as if the rumor came out before she married the
second guy, and that should now create a problem ותיתסר vetite'aser she
should be forbidden to the second guy. קא משמע לן דלא. Ka
mashma lan dela. So the one thing we say we're not going
to make problems for this poor woman is rumors. Only if there's
witnesses that the husband is still alive or if the husband shows
up, rumors not. But the fact will it be okay if she
married שלא ברשות, shelo birshut, which we mean based on two witnesses?
Because then we'll say she wasn't at fault and there's no need
to punish her, because there's no need to back up the testimony
of עד אחד. ed echad. In the end the גמרא Gemara says
no, we're not, it seems like we're not going to say that.
Now you will remember, we're going to assume that even if she's
not at fault all these things apply. You'll remember the גמרא Gemara
began the סוגיא sugya by quoting the statement of רב, Rav, הכי
הלכתא. hachi hilchata. Right, we rule like the line that maybe is
the line of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but we rule like that
if שלא ברשות shelo birshut she can go marry to the first
guy. But the end of the סוגיא, sugya, the thrust at the
end of the סוגיא sugya is no, it's we're not going to
rely on that. We're going to assume that's just the position of
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that even when she's not at fault. She’s
not at fault, she can’t go back, and the רי״ף Rif quotes
and he says all of the גאונים Geonim פסקן, pasken, the רי״ף
Rif from the רא״ש Rosh and all the גאונים Geonim פסקן, pasken,
even if it’s like the end of the סוגיא, sugya, that even
if it’s based on two witnesses and she’s completely not at fault,
and there was no need to back up this weak testimony of
one witness, nevertheless turns up the husband is still alive, he has
all of these negative consequences. Okay, so that actually is against the
פשט pshat approach of רב, Rav, so I want to again remind
you that we had a couple of אמוראים Amoraim that tried to
limit the scope of the משנה. Mishna. We had the statement of
רב Rav that says that if there’s two witnesses that the, that
she remarried based on two witnesses, it doesn’t matter even if the
guy shows up alive, right? Number one, which might mean the same
like this, that she can go back to the first husband or
might mean she can stay with the second husband. We had שמואל
Shmuel that says that if she contradicts the statement of the witnesses
or whatever, she can stay with the second guy. We have the
פסק psak that if it’s ניסת שלא ברשות, niset shelo birshut, whatever
that means, she can go back to her first husband. All those
limitations, the גמרא Gemara has basically rejected, and we’re basically left with
this broad scope that it’s always these negative consequences. The one exception
we’re left with at the end of the משנה Mishna if it’s
only a rumor that the guy is still alive, but otherwise we
have all these consequences. Now logically, as I said, you understand it
means that these negative consequences are not because we needed to punish
her to force her to do a better job in researching. It’s
just that these consequences are, the, these negative things are a natural
consequence of a reality of being as if she’s married to two
different men. But nevertheless, it’s a very now severe and very, you
know, very wide, wide-sweeping of
the cases in which we’re going to apply all of these rulings,
and that is how the גמרא Gemara and the הלכה halacha does
conclude. Charles, you’ve had your hand up for a while.
Quick question. On the issue of dating, I’ve never seen an actual
גט. get. Do we actually, would we actually say 2015 today?
No, I mean, you know what, I’m going to bracket that till
we get to גיטין Gittin because there’s a whole idea of counting
למנין שטרות, leminyan shtarot, and then there’s another, we do it like
למנין לבריאת העולם, leminyan lebriat haolam, and we do למנין שאנו מונים
כאן, leminyan sheanu monim kan, and there’s a question about a standardized
type of a dating or a local dating. You know what, I’m
going to bracket that.
I just, one reason I asked is that the Greek dating specifically
mentioned there was in use long after the Greek kingdom.
Yeah,
that’s מנין שטרות, minyan shtarot, right? If I’m remembering correctly. I’m not
sure that’s מלכות יון. malchut Yavan. מלכות יון Malchut Yavan means the
particular, well it’s true, you’re right. מנין שטרות minyan shtarot has to
do with a particular moment in Greek history. Right. But that’s called
מנין שטרות. minyan shtarot. I’m not sure that’s, and that actually is
how גיטין Gittin were, were dated. Let’s hold off on that till
we get to גיטין, Gittin, okay? Yeah.
Two related questions. Since the reading of the משנה Mishna in the
first place was kind of forced about this one witness, two witnesses,
there’s nothing there. And since in the end we reject all that
anyway, why did the גמרא Gemara put us through five days of
this one witness, two witness, when they’re going to reject it anyway?
And related to that, why do we need to wait to the
21st century for Dr. Friedman to point out what seems to be
so obvious if we are going to reject this one and two?
Yeah, you know, that’s a very good point because, because, you know,
you’re right. In a way what, you know, Dr. Friedman is saying
is not such a חידוש chiddush because it basically it emerges from
reading this דף גמרא daf Gemara and reading these משניות mishnayot in
גיטין Gittin that these negative consequences are not unique to the idea
of עד אחד ed echad and a way of backing up עד
אחד. ed echad. These negative consequences clearly seem related to some other
type of a phenomenon. So, you know, but I’ll just tell you
coming from a ישיביש Yeshivish background about having learned it, you so
internalize that beginning logic of the גמרא Gemara that sometimes you need
somebody to just reorient you to something that is pretty פשוט pashut
once you’re not, you know, haven’t already like internalized that whole perspective.
But you are right. But in a way what you’re saying is
that why should we have, why have they even in the ישיבות
Yeshivot internalized that perspective once you get to the end of the
גמרא Gemara that all these consequences apply even when she’s not at
fault and even in cases not based on עד אחד ed echad
and even in cases based on שני עדים? shnei eidim? Then how
can we continue to maintain at the beginning of the מסכת masechet
that that’s what it’s based on and how, right, you know? And
so I think that that really is an excellent question. And you
know, what you really would expect the ראשונים Rishonim to do is
not to say, oh look, by the end of the סוגיא sugya
we פסקן pasken it applies even by two witnesses. You would have
expected them to say, oh, since that’s how the סוגיא sugya ends,
let's figure out what the whole reason of this is based on.
You know, to some degree what they might say is in principle
it's based on the עד אחד ed echad case, but once we
said it in the עד אחד ed echad case, we then expanded
it even to the שני עדים shnei eidim case. Of course, even
to say that doesn't explain why we say it in all these
cases in גיטין, Gittin, which have nothing to do with testimony of
the dead husband. So you are right, it is shocking that the
more, you know, like you said, that the ראשונים ואחרונים Rishonim ve'Acharonim
didn't say by the time you get to the end of the
סוגיא sugya we have to reassess what we were saying in the
beginning. And I don't know why, I don't know why we don't
find more of that. You're absolutely correct. Yeah.
It seems that they did not make a distinction between all these
cases we just discussed where she should have had a lawyer, you
know, somebody go over
all this stuff.
But the two witnesses, there's no way that she could have reached
further than that. Right.
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. If we say that
in these cases she should have had a lawyer, then that would
say by the two witnesses though. is off the hook. But then
the גמרא Gemara says the
conclusion
is that it doesn't sound like the reason that these are true
is because she should have had a lawyer. It sounds like whether
she's at fault or not at fault, these are the consequences she
has to deal with.
Forget a lawyer. You're saying even there the husband just gives her
a גט. get.
Right, right. I understand. That's why, that's why it's very דחוק dachuk
to say that she had some fault in these cases. Okay, one
more question then we gotta move on, yes.
You just said just two seconds ago that if the guy comes
back and she disputes, that that's actually the second husband that that's
also too bad for her. Why would that be the case?
Because the guy's in front of us. And who do we care
what she disputes? גמרא Gemara sort of...
maybe she says oh he's got a birthmark and this doesn't have
the birthmark.
Yeah, but again that's- so that's the position of רב Rav and
שמואל, Shmuel, but in the end the גמרא Gemara more or less,
you know, rejected רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel or limited them to
cases to make them almost
moot.
Even if nobody- he just comes as a husband, no one else
recognizes him.
If nobody else recognizes him then yes we would believe her, but
if everybody recognizes him or if there are witnesses with him and
other people don't and then, you know, then the גמרא Gemara limited
the cases where her denial would work or wouldn't work. Okay, so
now we move on. So that was a very unexpected based on
exactly, you know, as we just pointing out, based because the whole
way the whole issue was framed it was all about the weakness
of עד אחד ed echad and now we get this unexpected ending
that even with two witnesses and even in other cases having nothing
to do with עד אחד, ed echad, same type of הלכה. halacha.
It passed though maybe at עד אחד ed echad though, right? At
least that...
Yeah, yeah. Well the קולא kula we פסקן pasken like the amazing
חידוש. chiddush. Let's not forget that with all these terrible negative consequences,
we still have the amazing חידוש chiddush that they let this woman
remarry based on hearsay evidence and עד אחד ed echad and very
flimsy type of evidence that would never pass in other cases. And
that's still the tremendous חידוש chiddush of חז"ל Chazal to allow her
to remarry.
She has to accept this if he shows up.
Exactly, exactly. So let's not forget the tremendous right leniencies that are
at play here as well. Yes, thank you, that's very important. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues. נישאת על פי בית דין תצא.
Niset al pi beis din teizei. If she marries based on בית
דין, beis din, now this is the end of the משנה Mishna
that in addition to the fact about whether these consequences apply, that
whether she has to bring a קרבן. korban. So when she does
it based on the authority of בית דין, beis din, she does
not bring a קרבן. korban. She committed adultery but it was under
a פסק psak of בית דין. beis din. When she does it
not based on the authority of בית דין, beis din, she does.
Now but again what does not based on the authority of בית
דין beis din mean? The simple sense means she just did it
on her own. She acted unilaterally. Oh, okay, my husband's dead, I'm
going to go get remarried. But the other but the way the
גמרא's Gemara been reading it is that there were two witnesses and
then she went ahead, but since it was two witnesses, it was
the strength of their testimony, not the פסק psak of בית דין.
beis din. And therefore when she goes ahead and she remarries, she's
not doing it based on under their official
authority, ironically because you have better evidence, you have two witnesses, and
therefore she has to bring a קרבן korban if it wound up
that she did that she did something wrong. So let's take a
look. Okay, so if it was על פי בית דין al pi
beis din she does not bring a קרבן. korban. אמר זעירי ליתא
למתניתין. Amar Zeiri, leisa lemasnisin. We don't rule like our משנה. Mishna.
מטעמי דבי מדרשא Mita'amei d'vei midrasha from what we taught in the
בית מדרש. beis medrash. דתני דבי מדרשא Detani d'vei midrasha we taught
in the בית מדרש. beis medrash. הורו בית דין ששקעה החמה. Hora
beis din sheshaka hachama. בית דין Beis din ruled that it was
sunset and people could go do מלאכה melacha and it was Saturday
night. ולסוף זרחה
U'lesof zaracha
and then it turned out that it was a cloudy day and
the sun was still was still hadn't set. אין זו הוראה אלא
טעות. Ein zu hora'a ela ta'us. That's not a פסק, psak, that's
an error. A פסק psak is a mistake in law, like a
you know a mistake in judgment of applying law to a particular
case. It's not a mistake in fact. A mistake in fact, it's
not like a פסק psak that was you know that was mistaken.
It's not a פסק psak at all. It was when the facts
were wrong, it completely isn't even seen as a פסק. psak. What's
the relevance of that? The relevance is that if you listen to
them, you don't say oh I don't have to bring a קרבן
korban because I was following their פסק. psak. You once- in retrospect
it turned out that we can't even call it a פסק psak
because it was based on mistaken fact. Okay, so therefore here too,
if they said she could remarry based on עד אחד ed echad
and it turned out the husband was alive, saying that's not a
פסק, psak, that's a mistake in fact. They thought the husband was
dead, it turned out he was alive. And therefore if this woman
went ahead and had sex with another man, she can't say I
was following their פסק psak and therefore I don't bring a קרבן
korban because retrospectively it wasn't a פסק, psak, it was a mistake
in fact, not a mistake in law. Okay, so that's what he
says.
So אלא טעות. ela ta'us. רב נחמן אמר הוראה היא, Rav Nachman
amar hora'a hi, it is a פסק. psak. Okay, אמר רב נחמן
תדע דהוראה היא, Amar Rav Nachman teida d'hora'a hi, I'll tell you
that even when there's a mistake in fact, it's still called a
פסק, psak, maybe a mistaken פסק psak but still a פסק. psak.
And therefore the person acting under its authority doesn't bring a קרבן.
korban. תדע דהוראה היא דבכל דוכתא כולי עד אחד לא מהימן. Teida
d'hora'a hi, d'bechol duchta kulei ed echad lo meheimen. Normally one witness
isn't believed. So And here we believe him. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama,
why? לאו משום דהוראה היא, lav mishum dehorahi, it must be that
the belief in the one witness is coming through the authority of
the בית דין. Beis Din. The בית דין, Beis Din, you know,
and they're using their authority and their judgment to believe the witness
is what Rashi says, it's their judgment, but not only their judgment,
their authority. Normally one witness doesn't count as evidence. So therefore, since
any time that they're פוסק posek in עד אחד, ed echad, it's
their authority, then therefore it's always seen as an act of פסק.
psak. It's not just seen as, you know, because you could also
say it's not just, here's another way of thinking about it. Is
it that בית דין Beis Din ruled based on a mistake in
fact, or is it that, do you say it wasn't even a
ruling? Did the sun set or not the sun set is not
a question of well, how did the בית דין Beis Din rule?
Was it sunset at 6:05 or not? Well, how did the rabbi
פסקן? pasken? What do you mean how did the rabbi פסקן? pasken?
Did the sun set or not set at 6:05? Right, so if
it's a question of fact, not a פסק psak based on fact,
if it's a question of fact, that's not even a פסק, psak,
that's a question of fact. So he's saying, this guy is alive
or dead, that's not a פסק psak question. How did the בית
דין Beis Din פסקן? pasken? What do you mean, it's a question
whether he's alive or dead. So it says, ah no, since we
did it based on one witness, it was something that was a
פסק psak issue. Right, whether the sun had set or not was
a question of fact, not a question of well, how did they
פסקן? pasken? But whether he's alive or dead on the basis of
one witness, that's something that requires their authority and therefore that's a
פסק psak issue and not just a question of fact.
Yes. But they're still both agreeing that the sunset, that's not even
a הוראה? horahi? He just, Rav Nachman just disagreeing on this?
Presumably yes, presumably on this case because it relies on עד אחד,
ed echad, he's not disagreeing on the sunset case. Yes. Okay.
This could be extrapolated to address the issue of the authority of
rabbis to make rules and you have to follow them or don't
have to follow them.
Yeah, so exactly, so all this ties into מסכת הוריות Masechet Horayos
absolutely. And Rashi and Tosfos are quoting how this ties into excerpts
from מסכת הוריות. Masechet Horayos.
Okay, so what would it signify if Rava just says it doesn't
matter?
Because now the question about whether he has to bring a קרבן
korban and there it might matter. Because if you do it under
the authority of בית דין, Beis Din, you don't bring a קרבן.
korban. The question is, is this a פסק psak of בית דין
Beis Din or is this just a question of fact? So Rav
Nachman says, of course it's a פסק psak of בית דין. Beis
Din. Yes, it's a פסק psak of בית דין Beis Din question,
you know, trying to determine, but since it's about with only one
witness and it's a and whatever and you need the special תורת
בית דין, toras Beis Din, it's a פסק psak of בית דין.
Beis Din. And therefore when she acts on it, she's off the
hook. At least in terms of a קרבן, korban, not in terms
of all the other negative consequences.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, I'm sorry, אמר רבא Amar Rava תדע דטעות
היא. teda detaus hi. No, it's not a פסק. psak. It's all...
the whole thing is an error. אי בעו בית דין בחלב ובדם
להתירא, I be'u Beis Din b'chelev u'v'dam l'heteira, if בית דין Beis
Din פסקן pasken let's say on some other type of a case.
The reason they give חלב chelev and דם dam is all this
is a question about the consequence of a קרבן. korban. So if
they פסקן pasken about forbidden fat or blood that it's permissible, והדר
חזו טעמא לאיסורא, vehadar chazu ta'ama l'issura, and then they realize that
they had made a mistake and פסקן pasken that it was forbidden.
Then כי הדרי ואמרי להתירא, ki hadri v'amri l'heteira, if they then
go ahead and find a reason to say it's מותר. mutter. Now
Rashi points out that the second time they said it was מותר
mutter after they פסקן pasken it was אסור assur was for a
weak reason. The stronger reason was still that it was אסור. assur.
So they realized they made a mistake, they realized the פשט pshat
is that it's אסור. assur. Then after they said, yeah, but we
have some weak thing to rely on our earlier פסק. psak. לא
משבחינן להו, lo mashbechinan lehu, we don't add that weaker idea, we
go by their stronger position that it's אסור. assur. Okay, that's if
you're dealing with a question of a question of law, not a
fact. Okay, so if your strong position is that it's true, you're
not going to go back and, I mean that it's forbidden, you're
not going to go back and revise it just because you have
another now new, as Rashi frames it, weak reason that it's מותר.
mutter.
That would be if you're dealing
with a question of law. ואילו הכא כי אתא עד אחד שרינא
לה. v'ilu hacha ki ata ed echad sharina lah. Here let's see
what would happen. One witness comes, says he's dead, we permit her.
אתו תרי אסרינא לה, atu srei asrina lah, two witnesses come, that's
the strong reason, we say she's forbidden. כי הדר אתא עד אחרינא
שרינא לה, ki hadar ata ed achrina sharina lah, now another witness
comes, we permit her. Now do we? Why is that so obvious?
Why isn't it like two against two? So the reason we permit
her now the second time is because the second עד אחד ed
echad who said he died, said he died after the two witnesses
said he was alive. Meaning עד אחד ed echad said he had
died on January 1st, two witnesses said no, on January 1st he
was alive. Then comes a witness says he had died on February
1st. Then we're going to believe the second witness because he's not
being contradicted by the first two. Okay. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's
the reason? לאו משום דטעות היא, lav mishum detaus hi, you see,
because this isn't just a question of judgment. If it was a
judgment, we have, oh, we have one reason to say this and
then we have a strong reason to say otherwise, and then we
have another weak reason to say that. If that was it, we
would go by our strongest argument about... that it's that she's אסור.
assur. But it's not an argument is she אסור assur or מותר.
mutter. It's a question of fact. So if it's a question of
fact, the last witness says something happened more recently, we'll believe the
last witness. Okay, it's a little funny analogy, but he's basically saying
bottom line here is we're trying to determine fact, it's not a
question of judgment. And therefore, if they make a mistake, it's not
a mistake in פסק, psak, at the end of the day, this
is just a question about facts. Okay.
Did they say anything if the two witnesses said
we just saw him this morning? Exactly. Okay. Anyway, so as it's
a little bit hard to understand exactly what the analogy is, but
nevertheless, that's the question: do you see this as a question of
פסק psak or a question of fact? And if it's a question
of פסק, psak, then she's off the hook. ורבי אליעזר סבר טועו
הוא. V'Rabbi Eliezer savar to'u hu. Rabbi Eliezer also holds that it's
a question of fact and error, and therefore she has to bring
a קרבן. korban. דתניא רבי אליעזר אומר יקוב הדין את ההר, De'tanya
Rabbi Eliezer omer yikov hadin et hahar, ותביא חטאת שמנה.
V'tavi chatat
shmena.
That the, again, the famous line from סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, the rule should
pierce through the mountain and she has to bring a nice fat
חטאת. chatat. Now the case there is, okay, so the case there
is, is a woman gets married out by בית דין, beis din,
and he says, and then it turns out the husband is alive,
so he says, you know, the bottom line is the facts have
to determine. That's the funny use of יקוב הדין את ההר. yikov
hadin et hahar. Sometimes that's sort of saying, "don't compromise," but here
he's saying the facts have to dictate and the husband was alive,
she's got to bring a חטאת. chatat. But okay, but she did
it based on בית דין. beis din. Again, you see, yes, but
it wasn't a question of פסק, psak, it wasn't a question of
law. It was a question of what were the facts at that
time, and therefore she's never, it's never ultimately the operating on בית
דין. beis din. Okay. אי אמרת בשלמא דטועו הוא, Ee amrit bishlama
de'to'u hu, if you say it's an error, משום הכי מייתיא קרבן,
mishum hachi matya korban, now that, and not a, you know, and
not
a פסק psak of בית דין, beis din, so then she'd bring
a קרבן. korban. אלא אי אמרת דהוראה היא, Ella ee amrit de'hora'ah
hi, if you say it's a פסק, psak, אמאי מייתיא קרבן? amay
matya korban? Why is she bringing a קרבן? korban? She's operating under
the authority of בית דין. beis din. It says, one minute, maybe
there's another reason. We've been assuming that when a person operates under
the authority of בית דין, beis din, under a פסק psak of
בית דין, beis din, they don't bring a קרבן. korban. Maybe that's
not true. ודלמא סבר רבי אליעזר יחיד שעשה בהוראת בית דין חייב?
V'dilma savar Rabbi Eliezer yachid she'asah b'hora'as beis din chayav? Maybe he
just holds in general that even if you're acting based on a
בית דין beis din פסק, psak, you have to bring a קרבן
korban if you made a mistake. So גמרא Gemara says no. אי
תני הכי מאי יקוב הדין את ההר? Ee ten hachi may yikov
hadin et hahar? Then why do you say, "oh no, the, you
know, the law has to pierce through"? That makes it sound like
it's unique to this case, it's not like he has a general
principle: anybody has to bring a קרבן korban regardless of what בית
דין beis din פסקו. paskin. It seems like it's something unique to
this case where he's saying, "I'm sorry, in this case she's got
to bring a קרבן." korban. Okay, so this is the idea that
if you do it on בית דין beis din you do, you
if, if בית דין beis din their פסק, psak, you don't bring
a קרבן. korban. But the question is, do we even call this
פסק? psak? Now again, it's quite funny and this goes back to
the point we were saying before. Until this point in the גמרא,
Gemara, we were assuming it's all the authority of בית דין. beis
din. Right? יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור דבר מן התורה, Yeish koach
b'yad chachamim la'akor davar min hatorah, though admittedly that was applied in
the גמרא Gemara in the ממזר mamzer context. But it's only עד
אחד, ed echad, and בית דין משום עגונה אקילו בה רבנן, beis
din mishum agunah kailu bo rabanan, and they, you know, wielded their
tremendous authority to מתיר matir her based on this and that stuff,
and דייקא ומינסבא dayka u'minsva and all of that stuff. And now
we're saying at the end, eh, it's not a פסק psak of
בית דין, beis din, eh, it's just a question about the facts.
Okay, but in a way that's consistent with the idea that also
we say that all these consequences apply even based on שני עדים.
shenei edim. Right? So it's by the end we're sort of in
a way not emphasizing so much the power and the unique role
that בית דין beis din is playing, right? We're saying that, you
know, that it's not so much she's doing it on the authority
of בית דין. beis din. Whether it was עד אחד ed echad
with the authority of בית דין, beis din, whether it was two
witnesses, all of the consequences apply. And therefore similarly, even if it's
עד אחד ed echad and it's the פסק psak of בית דין,
beis din, we don't really emphasize the פסק psak of בית דין.
beis din. We just say it was a question of fact and
the facts were wrong and therefore she has to bring a קרבן.
korban. And even though בית דין beis din פסקו, paskin, it's not
really something to be emphasized the authority of בית דין. beis din.
Okay, so that's at least how a number of these... it's not
conclusive, but that's how a number of these final opinions wind up.
And then the גמרא Gemara ends with the case about when
she...
but if she goes ahead and she does it based on two
witnesses, in that case presumably everybody agrees she goes ahead and she
brings her own, she does bring a קרבן. korban. Now I want
to just say a second about that. Like, what is this? Because
again, this does get to the בית דין beis din case. Why
is it when she does it on two witnesses, which is completely
something which is like, you know, she's an אנוסה, anusah, right? She's
two witnesses, she should totally have relied on them. And it turns
out that the guy was alive. Why does she bring a קרבן?
korban? Like, isn't she an אנוסה? anusah? Right, so what is the
logic when it says, right, לא נישאת
על פי בית דין תצא וחייבת בקרבן? lo nisset al pi beis
din teitzei v'chayevet b'korban? If לא נישאת על פי בית דין, lo
nisset al pi beis din, which means רש"י Rashi says אלא בעדים,
ella b'edim, חייבת בקרבן. chayevet b'korban. So how could it be that
if she does it based on witnesses she brings a קרבן, korban,
but based on בית דין, beis din, which is one witness, she's
off? So clearly what it's showing you is that the exemption of
קרבן, korban, right, is not just how much at fault she was.
That sometimes you bring a קרבן korban even if you're not at
fault. I'll give you an example. Famous example is the case in
the משנה Mishnah in שבת, Shabbos, which says the... or the גמרא
Gemara in the beginning of the seventh פרק perek of שבת, Shabbos,
that if somebody grows up thinking they're not Jewish, they were taken
captive, תינוק שנשבה, tinok she'nishba, they were raised amongst, with amongst Chinese
parents in the middle of mainland China, right? They never had any
clue even about Jews existing. And then, you know, when they're 40
years old they find out that they're Jewish, they still have to
bring a קרבן korban for the חילול שבת chillul Shabbos that they
did all those years. Now what type of fault did that person
have? Absolutely none. But it doesn't matter. Even if you had no
fault, it wasn't somebody who's holding a gun to your head. Somebody's
holding a gun to head it's like it's not, like you didn't
do it. You there, you know, at the end of the day
you did this action with no fault, but it was your action.
There's some rupture that's done, some sin in some metaphysical reality that
needs to be healed, that's done through a קרבן korban you have
to bring even if you have no fault. So even if somebody
has no fault, if they
did... The only thing that gets you off is what it makes
it not your act. So what makes it not your act? Well,
if a person held a gun to your head, it's not your
act. If בית דין Beis Din פסק-ed pasken it, then it's basically
their act, not yours, because you were just following orders, you know,
you were following their פסק. psak. You weren't arguing, you weren't acting
based on your own judgment, you were acting based on theirs, and
they had authority, and therefore that shifts the responsibility to them. Okay?
So that's why בית דין Beis Din gets you off of a
קרבן, korban, not just because it makes you faultless. In a case
where you're faultless you bring a קרבן, korban, but because it makes
it their problem, not your problem. But in the end, what the
גמרא Gemara is saying is that this question, is the husband alive
or dead, even based on עד אחד, ed echad, and even though
we emphasized before the tremendous authority of בית דין, Beis Din, we're
going to say that really wasn't their פסק, psak, it was really
just a question of fact. Again, quite an ironic end to everything
we've been saying until now. Yes, please.
Go ahead. So, you know, does it make a difference if these
two witnesses come and they brought them to בית דין Beis Din
and then בית דין Beis Din says, oh yeah, you know, we
believe, you know what I mean? Right, all done completely outside of
בית דין.
Beis Din. Right. So that's the thing as well that's not being
clear. When it's called the case, the גמרא Gemara calls the case
of two witnesses שלא על פי בית דין, shelo al pi Beis
Din, whether it was in the position of going back to the
husband or whether it was in the position of not bringing a
קרבן. korban. Did it really mean that they just listened to the
guys and acted? Or does it mean no? Presumably not. Presumably it
means because, let's face it, who's really acting outside of בית דין?
Beis Din? Nobody's going to have the חוצפה, chutzpah, I mean rarely,
to get remarried or whatever without getting a פסק. psak. Presumably it
means it was brought to בית דין Beis Din and בית דין
Beis Din validated it, but nevertheless, it wasn't seen as something that
required particularly their, you know, their exercising their special power, you know.
But yes, again, that even makes it more ironic. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara ends with this. הורו בית דין להנשא, horu Beis
Din l'hinasei, if they told her that she could go get married,
okay,
וקלקלה, vekilkela, she did something wrong, and it turns out that the
husband is alive, then even though she acted, they פסק-ed, pasken she
brings a קרבן, korban, because she didn't do what they had said.
Now, what did she do when they told her she could get
married? Well, she had sex without getting married. She had, right, she
just had sex outside of marriage. So then she can't say, oh,
they told me it was okay. Because they told you you could
get remarried; they didn't tell you that you could just סתם stam
have sex outside of marriage. So in that case, if the husband
turns up, she does have to, this is all now about bringing
a קרבן, korban, she does have to bring a קרבן. korban. She
can't shift the responsibility to them. That's what the משנה Mishnah says.
Got it? So they פסק-ed pasken she would be off the hook
because she was listening to them, but if she didn't do exactly
what they said, she went and she was קלקלה, kilkela, she acted
incorrectly. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say, מאי קלקלה, mai
kilkela, what was this incorrectly? רבי אליעזר אומר זנות, Rabbi Eliezer omer
zenus, she, you know, just had sex outside of marriage. רבי יוחנן
אומר אלמנה לכהן גדול גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט. Rabbi Yochanan omer almanah
le-kohen gadol grushah ve-chalutzah le-kohen hedyot. No, it wasn't סתם stam sex
outside of marriage, it was an actual איסור לאו, issur lav, meaning
we could have a whole discussion what exactly is the prohibition of
sex outside of marriage, but it's not, it's not a clear violation
of a negative prohibition like a אלמנה almanah marrying a כהן גדול
kohen gadol or a גרושה grushah marrying a normal כהן, kohen, which
is a real negative prohibition. Okay. So and also a case where
like they're not supposed to get married as opposed to if she
had sex with a single guy or whatever there was no איסור
issur in theory they could have gotten married. Okay. So, so and
that's when it's considered outside of the authority of בית דין Beis
Din and she would have to bring a קרבן. korban. But סתם
stam to have sex outside of marriage is not outside of the
authority that she was given or the permission she was given through
בית דין. Beis Din. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאן
דאמר זנות כל שכן אלמנה לכהן גדול. man d'amar zenus kol she-ken
almanah le-kohen gadol. If you say זנות zenus she has to bring
a קרבן korban that's outside of their פסק, psak, certainly by violating
a לאו lav like אלמנה almanah to a כהן גדול kohen gadol
is outside of their פסק. psak. אבל מאן דאמר אלמנה לכהן גדול
אבל זנות לא, aval man d'amar almanah le-kohen gadol aval zenus lo,
if you say no, only outside of their פסק psak is אלמנה
almanah כהן גדול kohen gadol but סתם stam sex outside of marriage
would not be it, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, because why? דאמרה, d'amra,
because she could say: אתון הוא דשויתן פנויה, atun hu de-shaviten pnuyah,
you told me that I was a פנויה. pnuyah. You told me
that my husband was dead, so even though you said you can
go get remarried, but essentially what you're פסק-ing pasken is my husband
is dead. So I am acting now based on that פסק. psak.
If my husband is dead, I'm allowed to go ahead and have
sex with another man. I'm not allowed to necessarily be a גרושה
grushah who's going to marry a כהן, kohen, okay, because you, but,
but by telling me I'm a פנויה, pnuyah, you might not like
the fact that I'm having sex outside of marriage, but that's consistent
with my status, so I'm not really operating in a way that
violates the status that you have recognized that I have, the status
I have as a פנויה. pnuyah. Okay. תני כוותיה דרבי יוחנן, tani
kevasei d'Rabbi Yochanan, it looks like רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. הורו בית
דין להנשא והלכה וקלקלה. horu Beis Din l'hinasei vehalcha vekilkela. בית דין
Beis Din פסק-ed pasken she should get married and she went and
she did it badly. What it means: כגון אלמנה לכהן גדול וגרושה
וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט, kegon almanah le-kohen gadol u-grushah ve-chalutzah le-kohen hedyot, like
it was a case again about a גרושה grushah marrying a כהן,
kohen, חייבת בקרבן, chayaves be-korban, in that case she's operating outside of
בית דין Beis Din and she has to bring a קרבן korban
if her husband shows up alive. על כל ביאה וביאה, al kol
biah u-biah, and how many קרבנות korbanos does she bring? Here's another
debate. על כל ביאה וביאה דברי רבי אלעזר, al kol biah u-biah
divrei Rabbi Elazar, for every act of sex that she had with
her husband, that's what רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says. Now, again, not
because sex of a גרושה grushah with a כהן kohen has a
קרבן, korban, it doesn't, that's a simple לאו, lav, but now because
it's seen as outside, because now it's an act of adultery, right?
The husband is alive, it's an act of adultery, which is חייב
chayav in a קרבן, korban, without the authority of בית דין, Beis
Din, without the permission of בית דין. Beis Din. So therefore every
act of sex is a separate קרבן. Korban.
If this was a regular גרושה Gerusha to a כהן? Kohen?
No קרבן. Korban.
But חכמים Chachamim over and over?
Yeah, but חכמים אומרים
קרבן אחד על כולם, Chachamim omrim korban echad al kulam, one קרבן
Korban for all the acts of sex. Okay, so that is a
question, it is a whole discussion in cases if a person does
multiple sins without being aware in the middle about anything, the person
has a whole table in front of them filled with חלב Cheilev
and thinks it is all permissible meat and eats over ten days
all of that stuff, do they bring a קרבן Korban for every
separate כזית Kezayis or is it one קרבן Korban for the whole
thing? Okay, ומודים חכמים לרבי אליעזר, Umodim Chachamim l'Rabbi Eliezer, and חכמים
Chachamim agree to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, שאם נישאת לחמשה בני אדם,
she'im nisayis l'chamisha b'nei adam, if she got married hopefully sequentially although
the problem here at the outset was she was married to two
men at the same time. But anyway, if she got married sequentially
to five different men, and in that
case שחייבת בקרבן על כל אחד ואחד, she'chayaves b'korban al kol echad
v'echad, that she brings a קרבן Korban for every separate man she
was married to, because sex with a different man is considered a
different type of an act and therefore a different קרבן. Korban.
But what about them? They also bring one, right? Don't they?
Yes, that is true as well. Yes, they also bring קרבן Korban
but we are focusing on her, but that is correct. Okay, so
that is the end, so again the end is that the גמרא
Gemara stands like it is all about the power of בית דין
Beis Din and the need to bolster עד אחד, Eid Echad, but
in the end we really seriously undercut that, we say that even
with two witnesses you have all these consequences and even with עד
אחד, Eid Echad, there is a serious questioning about how much is
it based on the authority of בית דין Beis Din or is
it a simple question of טעות. To'us. Okay, next משנה. Mishna. האשה
ששלח בעלה ובנו למדינת הים. Ha'isha she'shalach ba'alah u'vno l'mdinas hayam. So
a woman went and her
husband and son went to a far-away country.
ובאו ואמרו לה, U'va'u v'amru lah, witnesses came and said to her,
מת בעליך, meis ba'alaich, your husband died, ואחר כך מת בנך, v'acharkach
meis bincha, and then your son died.
So what does that mean? Because her husband died first, before her
son, she is not a she does not need יבום Yibum or
חליצה, Chalitza, because she has a living son and the son died
afterwards, now she is free to remarry without יבום Yibum or חליצה.
Chalitza.
ונישאת, V'nisayis, and she got married, and of course then what is
going to happen? ואחר כך אמרו לה חילוף היו הדברים, V'acharkach amru
lah chiluf hayu hadvarim, and then they said to her, and of
course why the second testimony is believed more than the first is
a big question, and is it the same witnesses or other witnesses?
We will bracket that for now and we will just assume that
now there is better evidence that it was the reverse, that first
the son died and then the husband, which would have meant that
she would have been required יבום Yibum or חליצה. Chalitza. Okay, so
תצא, taitzai, she has to leave the second guy, הולד ראשון ואחרון
ממזר, havlad rishon v'acharon mamzer, and the first and last son does
not mean the middle sons, it means all the kids, we will
see why it says first and last because there will be cases
where there will be a difference between beginning and end, but all
the kids are ממזרים. mamzerim. Okay, now of course that is a
little harsh, it might be that she married a man without having
gotten חליצה, chalitza, but okay, that is a simple לאו. lav. Why
is it that the kid is a ממזר? mamzer? It is not
like the cases before where it was a case that her husband
was still alive, it was a case of adultery. So the גמרא
Gemara is going to say this is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that
says that even in איסור לאו issur lav the kid is a
ממזר mamzer and therefore it is going to have all of these
negative consequences.
Wait, wait, wouldn't it not be a ממזר mamzer and then we
just make her
go get חליצה chalitza now? Presumably and we will discuss that in
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, what it also does not say is would
we say כל הדרכים האלו בה? kol hadrachim ha'elu bah? Right? Would
we say it has all these consequences in terms of תצא מזה
ומזה, taitzai mizeh u'mizeh, all those types of things, exactly, that is
also not so clear, because again, this is not the same, a)
the first husband is no longer alive, unlike both of the other
cases, where when the case actually was that she was currently married
to two husbands. Here the first husband actually does remain dead. And
second of all, the guy is that the second thing is not
the same type of severity of violation. But what it does say
is that the kid is a
ממזר. mamzer. אמרו לה, Amru lah, they said to her, מת בנך
ואחר כך מת בעליך. meis bincha v'acharkach meis ba'alaich. They said first
your son died then your husband died. So she
said okay, I am חייב chayav in יבום, yibum, ונתייבמה, v'nisyabma, and
then she
did יבום yibum with the
brother-in-law. ואחר כך אמרו לה חילוף היו הדברים, V'acharkach amru lah chiluf
hayu hadvarim, and
then
it turned out to be the reverse, again why we believe the
second one we will find out. So that means it turned out
that he basically has now done an איסור עריות issur arayos of
marrying
her husband's brother not in a case of יבום, yibum, which is
an איסור כרת, issur kares, in which case the kid is a
ממזר. mamzer. Okay. הקרבן? Ha-korban? תצא והולד ראשון ואחרון ממזר. Taitzai v'havlad
rishon v'acharon mamzer.
She has to get divorced and the kids that she has are
ממזרים. mamzerim. Again, why it says ראשון ואחרון rishon v'acharon we will
find out, but the kids are ממזרים. mamzerim. Again, that is a
simple straightforward הלכה. halacha.
More of an issue though is she still has to have חליצה
chalitza though.
Yeah, that is true. אמרו לה מת בעליך ונישאת ואחר כך
אמרו לה קיים היה ומת. Amru lah meis ba'alaich v'nisayis v'acharkach amru
lah kayam haya u'meis. And now this is like our first משנה,
mishna, your husband died. So she got remarried, then they said actually
he was alive.
And there's no kids, right?
No kids presumably, or whatever, no יבום yibum case, let's say they're
alive case, okay that's not a question. ואחר קיים היה ומת, ve'achar
kayam haya umes, and then she said actually when you remarried the
second guy, your husband was alive. Now he's dead, but he was
alive when he married the second guy. Okay, so that's like the
case of our first משנה Mishnah except that he just dies afterwards.
So in that case, תצא והולד ראשון ממזר ואחרון אינו ממזר. tetze
vehavlad rishon mamzer ve'achron eino mamzer. In that case, here's why we've
been mentioning the difference between ראשון Rishon and אחרון. Achron. The first
kid is a ממזר, mamzer, the kids she had until the husband
really died are ממזרים, mamzerim, right? Because she was then married and
these were, you know, with another man. But if they said yes,
he died, but now before he wasn't dead, now he's dead. Oh,
now he's dead. So she stays married now to the second guy,
the kids won't be ממזרים, mamzerim, right? Because now he actually is
dead. Now again, תוספות Tosfos says one minute, when our original משנה
Mishnah said, you know, that the kids are ממזרים mamzerim from the
ראשון Rishon and the אחרון, Achron, though I didn't get into this
with you, but תוספות Tosfos has a whole discussion that it might
mean even if the first guy gives her a גט get and
she wants to stay married to the second guy, right? We're going
to just have this whole קנס knas and say if you stay
married to the second guy, we're going to call those kids ממזרים
mamzerim even after you got your גט get from your first husband.
That's what תוספות Tosfos suggests in the first משנה. Mishnah. It sounds
like we're always going to call the kids ממזרים. mamzerim. Here not.
So again, the point is that this is talking not in terms
of Rabbinic הלכה, Halacha, the Rabbinic קנסות. knasot. This is just talking
at the דאורייתא de'oraisa level. All of this is a straight, not
with all these Rabbinic punishments and all that stuff, a straight דאורייתא
de'oraisa דין. din. So in the straight דאורייתא de'oraisa דין, din, if
she stays married to the second guy, the kids are not ממזרים.
mamzerim. Okay, afterwards.
אמרו לה מת
בעליך ונתקדשה,
Amru lah mes ba'aleich
veniskadsha, although she has to leave him...
תצא, tetze, right? That is true. The תצא tetze is Rabbinic. You're
correct about that. The תצא tetze is Rabbinic because now the guy
is, you know, because now the husband actually is dead and biblically
she'd be allowed to... so you're right. The תצא tetze is part
of, is Rabbinic. אמרו לה מת בעליך, Amru lah mes ba'aleich,
your husband died. Forget kids, we're not doing the kids. There are
live kids, that's not an issue in terms of יבום. yibum. ונתקדשה,
veniskadsha, and then the way this is different from the first משנה
Mishnah is it's not נישאת. niseis. She didn't start living with the
second guy. She just accepted כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin from the second
guy. ואחר בא בעלה, ve'achar ba ba'alah,
and then her husband comes. In that... so it's just like our
first משנה, Mishnah, except it's after קידושין, kiddushin, not after נישואין, nisuin,
which is a lot better. Why is it a lot better? Because
he hasn't had sex, because she hasn't been over on the איסור
issur of אשת איש eishes ish yet, right? It's just accepting
קידושין, kiddushin, and in terms of the approach that the problem is
that it looks like she's married to two husbands, if she hasn't
been living with the second guy, it doesn't really look like she's
married to the second guy. Okay, so this case is a lot
better. So in this case, מותרת לחזור לו, muteres lachazor lo, she
can go back to her first husband, אף על פי שנתן לה
אחרון גט, af al pi shenasan lah achron get, and even though
the second guy give her a גט, get, לא פסלה מן הכהונה,
lo paslah min hakehunah, it didn't invalidate because we basically, basically say,
we don't say, oh, you're somewhat married to the second guy, get
a גט. get. No, just go back to your first husband, don't
get a גט get from the second guy, nothing happened, no harm,
no foul. Your first husband was alive, the קידושין kiddushin wasn't good,
go back without a גט. get. So you understand what we're saying?
Not only does it not have all the negative consequences, she doesn't
even need a גט get from the second guy. So much so
that if the second guy said let's just play it safe and
I'll give you a גט get because it looks like we're married,
that גט get does not affect her status and she's not seen
as a גרושה, gerushah, and if her husband were now to die
she could marry a כהן. kohen. זו דרש רבי אליעזר בן מתיא,
zu darash Rabbi Eliezer ben Masya, אשה גרושה מאישה, ishah gerushah me'ishah,
a woman who's divorced from her husband a כהן kohen cannot marry,
ולא מאישינו אישה, velo me'isheino ishah, not if she gets a גט
get from a guy who isn't her husband. So what it's really
saying is, and again, this gets to the point that part of
all of the negative consequences are because it really looks like she's
married to the second guy and that's why she needs a גט
get and that's why the kids are ממזר mamzer and all these
types of things. Here where they haven't started living together and there's
not yet this sort of perception or facts on the ground as
if she's married to the second guy, she goes back to her
first husband and she doesn't even need a גט get and a
גט get won't even change her status. Okay, let's just read to
the bottom of the page because it's...
so people aren't going to be thinking, oh, people, you know, like
if you get קידושין kiddushin whatever, you know what I mean? Right,
we're not concerned about that sometimes.
I know, so we're not concerned about that. מאי ראשון ומאי אחרון?
mai rishon u'mai achron? What does it mean the first and the
last kids are not ממזר? mamzer? אילי ראשון לפני שמועה ואחרון לאחר
שמועה, ilei rishon lifnei shemuah ve'achron le'acher shemuah, kids she had with
this second husband, you know, in all these cases before the reversal
and then kids she had after the
reversal, ליתני הולד ממזר. lisni havlad mamzer. So okay, basically it's all
the kids she has with husband number two are ממזרים, mamzerim, so
just say the kids are ממזר. mamzer. Why do you mean first
and last? משום דקבעי למתני סיפא, mishum deka'ei lemsni seifa, no, all
the reason of framing it first and last is because of the
one case that we wanted to get to at the end. What
was the case we wanted to get to at the end where
there was a difference? אמרו לה מת בעליך ונישאת ואחר אמרו לה
קיים היה ומת, amru lah mes ba'aleich veniseis, ve'achar amru lah kayam
haya umes, they said your husband died, she got married, and then
they said actually he's been alive all this time, he just died
now. So in that case we have to distinguish between kids she
had before their testimony and kids she had after, right? Because in
that case, now he actually is dead, because in that case.
קיים היה ומת הראשון ממזר והאחרון אינו ממזר. Kayam haya umet harishon
mamzer vehacharon eino mamzer. So because we there had to distinguish between
kids before they testified and kids after they testified, after the second
pair testified, therefore תני נמי רישא ראשון ואחרון ממזר. tani nami reisha
rishon ve'acharon mamzer. Therefore in the beginning we say first and last,
but what we really should have said is kids are ממזר, mamzer,
kids are ממזר, mamzer, kids are ממזר, mamzer, meaning that's the הלכה,
halacha, yes, but in the end, the kids are ממזר mamzer and
before, you know, the testimony, after the testimony that the husband now
died, they're not ממזרים. mamzerim. Okay, and let's just read one more
line. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, זו דברי רבי עקיבא. zu divrei Rabi
Akiva. This משנה mishna that when she marries the second guy and
she needed to get חליצה chalitza and the kid is a ממזר,
mamzer, that's a רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva position, שהיה אומר אין קידושין
תופסין בחייבי לאוין, shehaya omer ein kiddushin tofsin bechayavei lavin, that even
if the simple לאו lav of like this woman not marrying a
man till she gets חליצה, chalitza, then there's no קידושין kiddushin and
if there's no קידושין, kiddushin, the kids are ממזרים. mamzerim. אבל חכמים
אומרים, Aval chachamim omrim, but the חכמים chachamim say אין ממזר מיבמה.
ein mamzer miyevama. There is no ממזר mamzer from a sister-in-law who
marries another man needing
חליצה. chalitza. ולימא אין ממזר מחייבי לאוין? Velima ein mamzer mechayavei lavin?
Why not make a more general statement: there's no ממזר mamzer by
a simple negative prohibition, it needs to be an איסור כרת? issur
kares? האי תנא הכי תנא דרבי עקיבא, Hai tanna hachi tanna deRabi
Akiva, no, because this is even within the position of רבי עקיבא.
Rabi Akiva. There's a debate when רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva says that
you can have a ממזר mamzer by a לאו, lav, does he
mean any לאו lav or only certain types of לאוין? lavin? So
this תנא tanna would say that when does רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva
say there can be a ממזר mamzer from an איסור לאו? issur
lav? דאמר מחייבי לאוין דשאר הוי ממזר. De'amar mechayavei lavin deshe'er havei
mamzer. It's an איסור לאו issur lav that's about relationship, שאר, she'er,
meaning about being a relative. What's a type of an איסור לאו
issur lav that mean most איסור לאוין issur lavin are not about
being a
relative? גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט, Grusha vechaluza lekohen hedyot, you know, this
case about a woman that can't marry somebody until she gets חליצה,
chalitza, that's not about relatives. The two לאוין lavin that are about
relatives that רש''י Rashi comes up with are: number one, a man
that your father had sex with that he never married, according to
some that's an איסור לאו. issur lav. And number two is marrying
a woman that you yourself did חליצה chalitza to. Okay, so therefore
that she was somewhat related to you because it was your brother's
wife, those are איסורי לאוין. issurei lavin. That's where there's a sense
of being a relative. There רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva says that's where
there's a ממזר. mamzer. But מחייבי לאוין גרידי, mechayavei lavin greidi, a
simple לאו, lav, like כהן kohen and a גרושה, grusha, or a
woman who needs חליצה chalitza who's marrying another man, לא הוי ממזר,
lo havei mamzer, would not be a ממזר. mamzer. And therefore they
might say that there are some לאוין lavin that are ממזר, mamzer,
but this case is not. So our משנה mishna that says the
kids are ממזר mamzer when this woman needed חליצה chalitza and married
another man because she believed the witnesses, that would only be according
to the most extreme position of רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva that says
even an איסור לאו issur lav that has nothing to do with
being a relative, the kids are still ממזרים, mamzerim, and that would
be the assumption, that is the position that our משנה mishna is
based on. Okay, so more about this tomorrow.
Aren't you all glad that I am back
and that we are now...